Kenneth Richards Papers
Kenneth Richards Papers
1945-1961
Richards, Kenneth, 1902-
4.5 linear feet
Papers of the American sportsman, inventor, businessman. Correspondence, 1947-58; patents and ideas for inventions, 1945-52; photographs; manuscript and published material. Papers relate primarily to Richard's inventions for shotguns and fishing tackle.
149541
Biographical History
Kenneth Richards (1902-??) was an American sportsman and inventor. He was an authority on guns and was the inventor of the "Shooting Master" choke and the Richards method for checking shotgun and ammunition performance. He spent much of his life in Massachusetts where he owned several businesses, including Master Chokes, Inc., The Shooting-Master Corp., and the True Art Fly Co.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Kenneth Richards Papers consists of correspondence, business files, manuscripts, patents and ideas, and a small amount of published material.
Correspondence is both incoming and outgoing and includes a small amount of correspondence by others.
Business files contains material related to Richards' various gun and fishing tackle businesses, and includes correspondence, photographs, publicity material, bills and receipts, and corporation records.
Manuscripts contains a typescript copy of Richards' pamphlet, "The Richards Quick Check Method for Checking Shotgun Patterns and Chokes."
Patents and ideas includes correspondence, patent applications, and sketches.
Published material contains copies of Richards' pamphlet, "The Richards Method for Checking Shotgun and Ammunication Performance."
Arrangement of the Collection
Richards' correspondence is arranged chronologically, correspondence by others is arranged alphabetically. Business files contain companies owned by Richards first, arranged alphabetically; related material follows, listed alphabetically by type. Patents are listed first alphabetically by type, followed by ideas (one folder of sketches).
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Science and medicine; Richards, Kenneth, 1902- -- Archives; Master Chokes, Inc.; The Shooting-Master Corp.; True Art Fly Co.; Archery -- Technological innovations.; Fishing tackle -- Technological innovations.; Shotguns -- Technological innovations.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Pamphlets.; Photoprints.; Inventors.; Sportsmen.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Of Richards
    - 1949-1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Of others
    - Richards, Mrs. Kenneth D., 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Richards, Paul C., 1961 (Box 1)
- Business files
  - Ken-Komp list of installations, 1947-1957 (Box 1)
  - Kenrich correspondence, 1947-1958 (Box 1)
  - Master Chokes, Inc.
    - Bills and receipts (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - 1950-1955, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1956-1958, undated, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Legal documents and corporation records, 1948-1956; undated (Box 3)
    - Noble Manufacturing Company, Inc., 1955-1956 (Box 4)
    - Publicity, 1956; undated (Box 4)
    - Stock certificates (Box 4)
  - The Shooting-Master Corp.
    - Bills and receipts (Box 4)
    - Contract (Shaughnessy, Richard), 1948 (Box 4)
    - Corporation records (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1958; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Publicity, 1948-1949; undated (Box 4)
    - Stock certificates, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
  - True Art Fly Co.
    - Bills and receipts (Box 4)
    - Contract (Westerfors, Eric), 1949 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 4)
    - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Account books
    - Bound, 1951-1957 (Box 5)
    - Unbound, 1948-1952; undated (Box 5)
  - Bills and receipts, 1946-1958; undated (Box 6)
  - Employees payroll record, 1948-1952 (Box 6)
  - Lures, 2 items (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Gardiner's Sporting Goods Store), undated (Box 6)
  - Publicity, 1949-1956; undated (Box 6)
  - Reference material, 1950-1956; undated (Box 6)
  - Shooting master chokes, 2 items (Box 6)
- Manuscripts
  - "The Richards Quick Check Method for Checking Shotgun Patterns and Chokes", undated; typescript (Box 6)
- Patents and ideas
  - Patents
    - Archery equipment
      - Arrow nock, 1949; undated (Box 7)
    - Fishing equipment
      - Fish lure body, 1946 (Box 7)
      - Fly box, 1948 (Box 7)
      - Signal device, 1948 (Box 7)
    - Guns
      - Shot patterning recoil compensator, 1948 (Box 7)
      - Interference claim, Powell v. Richards, 1944-1952; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous, 1948-1952 (Box 8)
  - Ideas
    - Sketch, floating internal baffle, adjustable shot tube, and gas diverter, 1952 (Oversize 1)
- Published material
  - "The Richards Method for Checking Shotgun and Ammunition Performance" (pamphlet), 1952 (Box 8)